<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Emad Mokhtar's Framework - career</title><link href="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/feeds/career.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/</id><updated>2018-04-09T19:00:00+03:00</updated><entry><title>Advice to Junior Developers</title><link href="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/advice-to-junior-developers.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-09T19:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-04-09T19:00:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Emad Mokhtar</name></author><id>tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2018-04-09:/advice-to-junior-developers.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="journey" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/oziel-gomez-555955-unsplash.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day I answered &lt;a href="https://www.quora.com/What-is-the-best-advice-you-can-give-to-a-junior-programmer/answer/Emad-Mokhtar"&gt;What is the best advice you can give to a junior programmer?&lt;/a&gt; question on Quora.com. I was shocked that my answer got many upvotes, so I thought to share my answer to this question on my blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let me acknowledge you that my answers …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="journey" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/oziel-gomez-555955-unsplash.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day I answered &lt;a href="https://www.quora.com/What-is-the-best-advice-you-can-give-to-a-junior-programmer/answer/Emad-Mokhtar"&gt;What is the best advice you can give to a junior programmer?&lt;/a&gt; question on Quora.com. I was shocked that my answer got many upvotes, so I thought to share my answer to this question on my blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let me acknowledge you that my answers are just my experience, what I missed during my career as software developer, and I wished someone told me this advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be humble be foolish be patient, you have a long journey of learning, so keep learning.&lt;/strong&gt; Technologies are changing so fast, so fast that you can't master everything, but you need to read about everything in software development, read blogs, news, etc. Invest your learning time in what you'll be master in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t be afraid to fail.&lt;/strong&gt; Making mistakes is a part of the learning, so please don’t be afraid to make mistakes, but learn from them. Even great software developers got fired, made mistakes, and they feel down, but what makes them great that they get up and learn from mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/the-ten-commandments-of-egoless-programming/"&gt;Read about The Ten Commandments of Egoless Programming &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; You will need these commandments during your journey, They helped me in &lt;a href="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/being-a-team-member.html"&gt;my first job with a team&lt;/a&gt; and they are so nice that I want to print them as a poster and hang it on my home office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read other developers code.&lt;/strong&gt; Github is your friends, so pick some projects and start to read their codes, when I tried to contribute to Django project for the first time, I was not understanding anything from the code, and you'll feel the same first time, don't worry ask someone (Check the next point) and learn to read someone else code. One day during my tech interview the interviewee told me that what you are missing it reading Python code, please go read Python source code, dig deep into it, and learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask, ask, ask, ask, and ask.&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, like I said in point number 1 be humble, so keep asking your mates and other programmer and learn from them, and listen and evaluate after that, don't take everyone's advice with research, please don't do research to prove they are wrong, do the research to get second opinion and learn more about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;THERE IS NO ROCKSTAR/NINJA/GURU developer&lt;/strong&gt; it is a marketing word, and they are not true, nice programmers are making mistakes and they are not superheroes, there are some companies that advertise they need Ninja, Rockstar or Guru developer, no way they do not exist and they won't, developer are human who make mistakes, learn, and improve. In other words, it is a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_craftsmanship"&gt;craftsmanship&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read books about the career beside learning the tools/language/framework, programming is not about writing code only.&lt;/strong&gt; Here is my list of &lt;a href="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/how-do-i-learn.html"&gt;books to read&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write a blog.&lt;/strong&gt; Start a blog and write what you have learned during your day, and write is as your source of knowledge. I started this one for this purpose and many times I'll return to my blog to get the information I need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contribute to open source software.&lt;/strong&gt; You will learn a lot from contributing to open source project, so you will learn, helping the community, and the maintainers will be happy. Start small and learn more about the project, start with a framework/tool you are using, there are so many ways to contribute to open source projects, you can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Report a bug.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reproduce the bug, and write how to reproduce it on the ticket.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Translate the software or the documentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write some code to fix a bug or implement a new feature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enjoy the journey.&lt;/strong&gt; You need to enjoy the journey, it won't be an easy one, and you will have some difficult times, but remember to be patient, and like what you are doing to keep going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="career"></category><category term="developer"></category><category term="programmer"></category></entry><entry><title>Being a Team member</title><link href="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/being-a-team-member.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-10T12:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-02-10T12:00:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Emad Mokhtar</name></author><id>tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2018-02-10:/being-a-team-member.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Team" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/karen-maes-310484.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style="background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px;" href="https://unsplash.com/@karen1974?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Karen Maes"&gt;&lt;span style="display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px;"&gt;&lt;svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" style="height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white;" viewBox="0 0 32 32"&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d="M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z"&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px;"&gt;Karen Maes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Start&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In September 2017 I left my job and my life in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuwait"&gt;Kuwait&lt;/a&gt; and traveled to the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netherlands"&gt;Netherlands&lt;/a&gt; to join &lt;a href="https://veneficus.nl/en/"&gt;Veneficus&lt;/a&gt; as Software developer, one of the reasons I moved to the Netherlands is to work in a team and I started to feel being a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Team" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/karen-maes-310484.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style="background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px;" href="https://unsplash.com/@karen1974?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Karen Maes"&gt;&lt;span style="display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px;"&gt;&lt;svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" style="height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white;" viewBox="0 0 32 32"&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d="M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z"&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px;"&gt;Karen Maes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Start&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In September 2017 I left my job and my life in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuwait"&gt;Kuwait&lt;/a&gt; and traveled to the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netherlands"&gt;Netherlands&lt;/a&gt; to join &lt;a href="https://veneficus.nl/en/"&gt;Veneficus&lt;/a&gt; as Software developer, one of the reasons I moved to the Netherlands is to work in a team and I started to feel being a &lt;a href="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/solo-developer.html"&gt;solo developer&lt;/a&gt; is bad for my career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I joined a team of 7 developers mixed between full-time and part-time, and start to fell there are some missing skills I need to develop, and yes I was correct I worked alone for almost 7 years. What is it mean working alone? it means no need for communication, no need for development plans, no need for technical debates, no need to manage your time or other team member's time. In the beginning, I feel so bad and stressed with that change, to be honest, I made many mistakes, but with a growth mindset you need to learn from mistakes and grow and fix them, os what I did?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Community Help!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I asked for community help, I went to &lt;a href="https://www.pythonistacafe.com/"&gt;PythonistaCafe&lt;/a&gt; forum and posted my situation and the members gave me great answers regarding my situation, and one member point me to something very useful and first time to know it, which is the Egoless Developer and The 10 Commandments of Egoless Programming, they pointed me to links to posts to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are links:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/the-ten-commandments-of-egoless-programming/"&gt;Jeff Atwood post about egoless developer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://wiki.c2.com/?EgolessProgramming"&gt;EgolessPRogramming C2.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Team Help!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I asked my team members, and my manager, yes I asked my team for help, and I found out they really helped and they understand my problem. I found out I'm not alone, we as developers have many in common issues, and it is addressed in books and community for many years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Final thought&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please don't hesitate to ask for help from the community or your teammates, yeah it is not an easy step to take, but it is not bad and hard as you think, it is easy and you'll get good benefits from it 😉. You find you are not lone and many developers in your community faced the same issues, so the community can help you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Last but not least, &lt;a href="https://veneficus.nl/en/working-at/"&gt;Veneficus is hiring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="career"></category><category term="work"></category><category term="netherlands"></category></entry></feed>