<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Emad Mokhtar's Framework - Emad Mokhtar</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/</link><description>Geek developer who's in search of code perfection.</description><lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 12:00:00 +0300</lastBuildDate><item><title>I tired Nodejs and I like it</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/i-tired-nodejs-and-i-like-it.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The Sign" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/austin-chan-275638-unsplash.jpg"&gt;
Photo by Austin Chan on Unsplash&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a chance to try Node.js framework last month; I decided to build REST APIs using &lt;a href="https://nodejs.org/en/"&gt;Node.js&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://expressjs.com/"&gt;express.js&lt;/a&gt;. Regularly I'm using JavaScript in my daily work besides using &lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com/"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt; to build Web Applications, but many times I need to develop a front-end feature, This when I need to use JavaScript. I'm always using JavaScript to write front-end logic, but I never wrote back-end logic using it. I took the challenge to develop a simple REST APIs using &lt;a href="https://expressjs.com/"&gt;express.js&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src="https://giphy.com/embed/d4zHnLjdy48Cc" width="480" height="350" frameBorder="0" class="giphy-embed" allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Development environment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start developing, I need to get my machine ready, so I installed &lt;a href="https://nodejs.org/en/"&gt;node.js&lt;/a&gt; via Homebrew (I'm a macOS user), it is quite easy, and node.js installation comes with &lt;a href="https://www.npmjs.com/"&gt;npm&lt;/a&gt; "npm is a package manager for node.js it is like &lt;a href="https://pypi.org/"&gt;pypi&lt;/a&gt; or pip for Python". I used &lt;a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/"&gt;Visual Studio Code&lt;/a&gt; as a text editor. Now I'm ready to go 💪🏻.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I've learned?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While building the REST APIs, I've learned many things, mainly that I'm experiencing the new development stack. Let's see the parts I've learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Node.js&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nodejs.org/en/"&gt;Node.js&lt;/a&gt; is a back-end engine; it is using Google Chrome V8 JavaScript engine to run JavaScript code …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2018 12:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2018-12-31:/i-tired-nodejs-and-i-like-it.html</guid><category>Python</category></item><item><title>Thank you Python 🐍 community</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/thank-you-python-community.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="thank you" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/thank-you-community.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;November 2015 &lt;a href="http://emadmokhtar.com/net-developer-comfort-zone.html#net-developer-comfort-zone"&gt;I left my comfort zone, and I started my journey with Python&lt;/a&gt;, it was not an easy start. I was a Windows/Microsoft guy, I was using Microsoft Visual Studio on a daily basis, and Windows was my primary OS.  I switched to macOS and Pycharm; I picked these to make my transition easier than using Linux (Ubuntu) and Vim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 2 months of figuring out what are virtualenv, pip, python version, and environment variable. I started another milestone of how to write a pythonic code while that I went to &lt;a href="http://emadmokhtar.com/djangocon-europe-2016-me-and-django-sprints.html#djangocon-europe-2016-me-and-django-sprints"&gt;DjangoCon&lt;/a&gt;, and I saw how awesome this community is. WOW 🤗, this community is very welcoming for newcomers, and since this day I'm in ❤️ with this community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like someone said to me "You are staying because of people not because of  the language." Indeed, the community is excellent 👍🏻, and it is what makes this language impressive and always adopting the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to thank all human beings in this community form leaders to the starters (welcome BTW 😉), thank you for being a part of this community and making this community.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2018 12:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2018-09-23:/thank-you-python-community.html</guid><category>Python</category></item><item><title>Advice to Junior Developers</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/advice-to-junior-developers.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="journey" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/oziel-gomez-555955-unsplash.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day I answered &lt;a href="https://www.quora.com/What-is-the-best-advice-you-can-give-to-a-junior-programmer/answer/Emad-Mokhtar"&gt;What is the best advice you can give to a junior programmer?&lt;/a&gt; question on Quora.com. I was shocked that my answer got many upvotes, so I thought to share my answer to this question on my blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let me acknowledge you that my answers are just my experience, what I missed during my career as software developer, and I wished someone told me this advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be humble be foolish be patient, you have a long journey of learning, so keep learning.&lt;/strong&gt; Technologies are changing so fast, so fast that you can't master everything, but you need to read about everything in software development, read blogs, news, etc. Invest your learning time in what you'll be master in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t be afraid to fail.&lt;/strong&gt; Making mistakes is a part of the learning, so please don’t be afraid to make mistakes, but learn from them. Even great software developers got fired, made mistakes, and they feel down, but what makes them great that they get up and learn from mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/the-ten-commandments-of-egoless-programming/"&gt;Read about The Ten Commandments of Egoless Programming &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; You will need these commandments during your journey, They helped me in &lt;a href="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/being-a-team-member.html"&gt;my first job with a …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2018 19:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2018-04-09:/advice-to-junior-developers.html</guid><category>career</category><category>developer</category><category>programmer</category></item><item><title>Let's build it</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/lets-build-it.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="idea" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/james-pond-185593-unsplash.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style="background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px;" href="https://unsplash.com/@shotbyjamespond?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from James Pond"&gt;&lt;span style="display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px;"&gt;&lt;svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" style="height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white;" viewBox="0 0 32 32"&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d="M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z"&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px;"&gt;James Pond&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Discovery&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After many years of developing web applications, I found my passion is building Web APIs. so why I like it, I like it because I think it's giving your application a power to integrate with other apps (desktop, mobile apps, etc.), other devices (Amazon Dot, Google Home, etc.),  sensors (RaspberryPi, Arduino, etc.), and bots (Slack, Telegram, Facebook Messanger, etc.).
Can you feel the power that Web API that can add to your apps?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Let's build something&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I found my passion and start to search for a project to ably what I like and keep developing it. I found that there is no Web API for &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tafsir"&gt;Quran Tafseer/Translation&lt;/a&gt;. What can Quran Tafseer API do for developers? If you want to develop an application for Quran and you want to provide a Tafseer/Translation to the application users, you need to gather the information from more than one source. I found most of the existing applications done it and after that work, app developers will keep this information available to their app only, so I thought of doing this work for the community and provide Tafseer/Translation for free as Web API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Stages&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stage I&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 04 Mar 2018 12:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2018-03-04:/lets-build-it.html</guid><category>side-project</category><category>django</category><category>python</category></item><item><title>Being a Team member</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/being-a-team-member.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Team" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/karen-maes-310484.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a style="background-color:black;color:white;text-decoration:none;padding:4px 6px;font-family:-apple-system, BlinkMacSystemFont, &amp;quot;San Francisco&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Helvetica Neue&amp;quot;, Helvetica, Ubuntu, Roboto, Noto, &amp;quot;Segoe UI&amp;quot;, Arial, sans-serif;font-size:12px;font-weight:bold;line-height:1.2;display:inline-block;border-radius:3px;" href="https://unsplash.com/@karen1974?utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=photographer-credit&amp;amp;utm_content=creditBadge" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" title="Download free do whatever you want high-resolution photos from Karen Maes"&gt;&lt;span style="display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px;"&gt;&lt;svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" style="height:12px;width:auto;position:relative;vertical-align:middle;top:-1px;fill:white;" viewBox="0 0 32 32"&gt;&lt;title&gt;unsplash-logo&lt;/title&gt;&lt;path d="M20.8 18.1c0 2.7-2.2 4.8-4.8 4.8s-4.8-2.1-4.8-4.8c0-2.7 2.2-4.8 4.8-4.8 2.7.1 4.8 2.2 4.8 4.8zm11.2-7.4v14.9c0 2.3-1.9 4.3-4.3 4.3h-23.4c-2.4 0-4.3-1.9-4.3-4.3v-15c0-2.3 1.9-4.3 4.3-4.3h3.7l.8-2.3c.4-1.1 1.7-2 2.9-2h8.6c1.2 0 2.5.9 2.9 2l.8 2.4h3.7c2.4 0 4.3 1.9 4.3 4.3zm-8.6 7.5c0-4.1-3.3-7.5-7.5-7.5-4.1 0-7.5 3.4-7.5 7.5s3.3 7.5 7.5 7.5c4.2-.1 7.5-3.4 7.5-7.5z"&gt;&lt;/path&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="display:inline-block;padding:2px 3px;"&gt;Karen Maes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Start&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In September 2017 I left my job and my life in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kuwait"&gt;Kuwait&lt;/a&gt; and traveled to the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Netherlands"&gt;Netherlands&lt;/a&gt; to join &lt;a href="https://veneficus.nl/en/"&gt;Veneficus&lt;/a&gt; as Software developer, one of the reasons I moved to the Netherlands is to work in a team and I started to feel being a &lt;a href="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/solo-developer.html"&gt;solo developer&lt;/a&gt; is bad for my career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I joined a team of 7 developers mixed between full-time and part-time, and start to fell there are some missing skills I need to develop, and yes I was correct I worked alone for almost 7 years. What is it mean working alone? it means no need for communication, no need for development plans, no need for technical debates, no need to manage your time or other team member's time. In the beginning, I feel so bad and stressed with that change, to be honest, I made many mistakes, but with a growth mindset you need to learn from mistakes and grow and fix them, os what I did?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Community Help!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I asked for community help, I went to &lt;a href="https://www.pythonistacafe.com/"&gt;PythonistaCafe&lt;/a&gt; forum and posted my situation and the members gave me great answers regarding my situation, and one member point me to something …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 10 Feb 2018 12:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2018-02-10:/being-a-team-member.html</guid><category>career</category><category>work</category><category>netherlands</category></item><item><title>Book Review: The Subtle Art of Not Giving a F**k</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/book-review-the-subtle-art-of-not-giving-a-fk.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Book cover" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/the-subtle-art.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last month I had small trip to Netherlands, Rotterdam, at night I went to have a dinner with friends at &lt;a href="http://www.euromast.nl/en"&gt;EuroMast&lt;/a&gt;, it was windy day, we putted our bags in my friend’s car trunk, but unfortunately someone broken inside the car and took 2 bags and one of them was my bag. My travel backpack is stolen and I lost most of my gadgets (MacBook Pro, iPad, Amazon Kindle, Wallet, etc..)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a night at the police station to report the incident, I went to hotel to get some sleep before flying back to home, next day I woke up, prepared my bags and headed to airport, but on my way to the airport I was thinking what to do during my long flight, I thought let’s read a book, so once I reached the airport I went to bookstore and bought &lt;a href="http://amzn.to/2nmdr0B"&gt;The Subtle Art of Not Giving a F**k&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Emad, Why you are telling us these story? Because while I'm reading this book I found this part&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don't always control what happens to us. But we always control how we interpret what happens to us, as well as how er respond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which is what …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2017 12:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2017-03-22:/book-review-the-subtle-art-of-not-giving-a-fk.html</guid><category>book</category><category>review</category></item><item><title>Client side validation for Django Forms</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/client-side-validation-for-django-forms.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Parsley" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/parsley.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.lovethegarden.com/sites/default/files/styles/full_width_700/public/images_and_media/parsley.jpg?itok=X7psNkrF"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In DUTH 2016 there was a session for &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/uzTaWKcMzos"&gt;Django Validation by Loïc Bistuer&lt;/a&gt;, in the session Loïc showed many areas you can validate user inputs from Django Form way to the Database Engine. To be honest validation in Django is a piece of cake and even if there is special validation rules you want to implement, you can still implement it, as I said it is easy and straight forward in Django, all of these validation is server side which happen on web server not on client-side, so what about client side?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What is client side validation?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In simple way, client side validation is validation user input on browser before sending the data to sever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is good practice to validate user inputs from client side to save roundtrips to server, but it needs extra work to implement your validations using JavaScript or using HTML5 form validation, but there is a way to replicate Django form validation to client side, let’s see how.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Django Parsley&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/agiliq/Django-parsley"&gt;Django Parsley&lt;/a&gt; is a Django app that replicate Django Form validation to client side using &lt;a href="http://parsleyjs.org"&gt;ParsleyJS&lt;/a&gt; library, and it’s so easy to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How to use Django Parsley?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Install Django Parsley …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2017-03-08:/client-side-validation-for-django-forms.html</guid><category>Django</category><category>Forms</category></item><item><title>Django is boring but you can contribute</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/django-is-boring-but-you-can-contribute.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Bored employee in front of computer" src="http://blog.inf.ed.ac.uk/sapm/files/2014/03/boredom.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I attended Django Under The Hood 2016, in sprints there is a comment passing around which &lt;a href="https://www.caktusgroup.com/blog/2016/12/14/django-boring-or-why-tech-startups-should-use-django/"&gt;Django is boring&lt;/a&gt;. Django is boring is actually a good news for the framework users, but it's sad one for developers want to contribute to the framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time I go to check &lt;a href="https://code.djangoproject.com/"&gt;Django tickets&lt;/a&gt; to contribute, I found they are difficult and in depth, because Django is a mature project now and the amount of contribution needed to the codebase is rare, but if you want to contribute you can check &lt;a href="https://code.djangoproject.com/query?status=!closed&amp;amp;easy=1"&gt;easy pickings&lt;/a&gt; tickets. In DUTH before the sprints projects leaders start to ask attendees for contributions, I found this is a good opportunity for me and for anyone wants to help the community and start to contribute to Django community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Github duth contributions" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/duth-contribution.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to contribute to Django and help the community, I have some suggestions for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write blog posts on How-tos, tips, and tutorials for Django, and &lt;a href="https://djangopackages.org/"&gt;Django packages&lt;/a&gt; for example Django REST Framework.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Help Django team to &lt;a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.10/internals/contributing/triaging-tickets/#triage-workflow"&gt;move the ticket from stage to another&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contribute to one of Django’s packages, specially packages you are using, check their github page and help them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tried more than one package for X …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2017-01-08:/django-is-boring-but-you-can-contribute.html</guid><category>community</category><category>Django</category><category>duth</category></item><item><title>Add isort and flake8 test to your Django Project</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/add-isort-and-flake8-test-to-your-django-project.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Unit Test Works" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/unit-test-works.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I'll tell you how to add isort and flake8 tests to your Django project test suite, this is simple script and you can start from this point and customize you own test suite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As they said Django is a “batteries included” web application framework, and one of the batteries is Testing framework, &lt;a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/dev/topics/testing/"&gt;testing in Django&lt;/a&gt; is easy and you can start writing tests even if you didn't do it before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you ever work with Django, you will write tests for your project, to test your views, models, forms, etc.. but it's better if you can add &lt;a href="https://github.com/timothycrosley/isort"&gt;isort&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://flake8.pycqa.org/en/latest/"&gt;flake8&lt;/a&gt; tests to maintain the quality of your Python code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Installation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need some packages first so we can run the tests&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;pip install flake8 isort flake8-isort
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's better to create and use sperate virtualenv&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Configurations&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;flake8-isort is using &lt;code&gt;.isort.cfg&lt;/code&gt; file to run the isort test against it, so let's add our configuration file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.isort.cfg file&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;[*.py]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;max_line_length&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;120&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;indent_style&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;space&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;indent_size&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;known_first_party&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;isort&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;ignore_frosted_errors&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;E103&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;skip&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;runtests.py,build,.tox&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;balanced_wrapping&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="na"&gt;not_skip&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;__init__.py&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;Test Python Script&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it's time to write the Python script to run Django, isort, &amp;amp; flake8 tests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;runtests …&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 27 Sep 2016 18:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2016-09-27:/add-isort-and-flake8-test-to-your-django-project.html</guid><category>django</category><category>python</category><category>unittest</category><category>howto</category></item><item><title>How to run Celery as daemon?</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/how-to-run-celery-as-daemon.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="celery smoothy" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/celerysmoothie.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Install upstart script&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Permissions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to make the user which will be used to run celery an owner of &lt;code&gt;log&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;run&lt;/code&gt; directories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sudo chown -R root:root /var/log/celery/
sudo chown -R root:root /var/run/celery/
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Celery upstart&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1- Download &lt;code&gt;celeryd&lt;/code&gt; file from &lt;a href="http://github.com/celery/celery/tree/3.1/extra/generic-init.d/"&gt;Celery official github repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2- Copy &lt;code&gt;celeryd&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;/etc/init.d/celeryd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sudo cp celeryd /etc/init.d/
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;3- Make it executable&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sudo chmod +x celeryd
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;4- Make it run on startup&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sudo update-rc.d celeryd defaults
sudo update-rc.d celeryd &lt;span class="nb"&gt;enable&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;5- make it owned by root&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sudo chown root:root celeryd
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;6- Done, now you can start/stop/restart celeryd as service&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sudo service celeryd start
sudo service celeryd stop
sudo service celeryd restart
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Celerybeat upstart&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1- Download &lt;code&gt;celerybeat&lt;/code&gt; file from &lt;a href="http://github.com/celery/celery/tree/3.1/extra/generic-init.d/"&gt;Celery official github repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2- Copy &lt;code&gt;celerybeat&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;/etc/init.d/celerybeat&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sudo cp celerybeat /etc/init.d/
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;3- Make it executable &lt;code&gt;sudo chmod +x celerybeat&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4- Make it run on startup&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sudo update-rc.d celerybeat defaults
sudo update-rc.d celerybeat &lt;span class="nb"&gt;enable&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;5- make it owned by root&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sudo chown root:root celerybeat
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;6- Done, now you can start/stop/restart celerd as service&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;sudo service celerybeat start
sudo service …&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 15:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2016-09-20:/how-to-run-celery-as-daemon.html</guid><category>django</category><category>python</category><category>celery</category></item><item><title>DjangoCon Europe 2016, me, and Django Sprints</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/djangocon-europe-2016-me-and-django-sprints.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="djangocon logo" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/yay.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="djangocon name tag" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/Name-tag.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Late in 2014 I decided to shift my development stack from Microsoft .NET Framework to &lt;a href="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/my-first-django-app.html"&gt;Django/Python stack&lt;/a&gt;. It's been almost 2 years now and I'm really enjoying and learning many things. I'm so happy that I've done this leap.
In 2016 I had the change to attend DjangoCon Europe 2016 at Budapest, Hungry. I enjoyed it to the maximum, it's my first time to meet the community, and it's first time attending one of Django community events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Django Community&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started to learn Django, I found everyone is recommending Django documentation itself as start, from my past experience in .NET framework that its documentation is not enough to get your head around the framework, you need at least to read one book or watch one video course, but after reading Django official documentation, I was shocked that it's enough as start, it's enough for your daily tasks, it's enough to dive in Django framework, or fixing issues. The quality of &lt;a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/dev/"&gt;Django official documentation&lt;/a&gt; is amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I went to DjangoCon Europe 2016 I saw people reflecting the philosophy of Django framework, the community is so welcoming as Django documentation, I had the chance to meet  &lt;a href="https://github.com/freakboy3742"&gt;Russell Keith-Magee&lt;/a&gt; and …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2016-09-07:/djangocon-europe-2016-me-and-django-sprints.html</guid><category>community</category><category>Django</category><category>DjangoCon</category></item><item><title>PACKT publishing ebooks and videos 50% discount offer</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/packt-publishing-ebooks-and-videos-50-discount-offer.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Generously PACKT publishing is offering 50% discount on Python and Django ebook and videos. PACKT has many Python ebooks and videos from novice to advanced level, it one of the most publishing company that releases books and videos for Python and Django, If you tried to Google a book for Python or Django, you differently will find one of their books in the search results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interesting ebooks and videos for Python:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.packtpub.com/big-data-and-business-intelligence/python-machine-learning"&gt;&lt;img alt="Python Machine Learning" src="https://www.packtpub.com/sites/default/files/5130OS_Python%20Machine%20Learning_.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.packtpub.com/big-data-and-business-intelligence/mastering-python-video"&gt;&lt;img alt="Mastering Python" src="https://www.packtpub.com/sites/default/files/bookretailers/9781783988969.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.packtpub.com/big-data-and-business-intelligence/python-data-analysis"&gt;&lt;img alt="Python DAta Analysis" src="https://www.packtpub.com/sites/default/files/3358OS_cov.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.packtpub.com/application-development/geospatial-development-example-python"&gt;&lt;img alt="Geospatial Development by Example Python" src="https://www.packtpub.com/sites/default/files/2355OS_4558_Geospatial%20Development%20by%20Example%20with%20Python.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interesting ebooks and videos for Django:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.packtpub.com/web-development/web-development-django-cookbook-second-edition"&gt;&lt;img alt="Web Development Django Cookbook" src="https://www.packtpub.com/sites/default/files/6775O9S_Web%20Development%20with%20Django%20Cookbook-%20Second%20Edition.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.packtpub.com/web-development/django-example"&gt;&lt;img alt="Django By Example" src="https://www.packtpub.com/sites/default/files/B03922_Django%20By%20Example_.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.packtpub.com/web-development/mastering-django-web-development-video"&gt;&lt;img alt="Master Django Web Developement" src="https://www.packtpub.com/sites/default/files/bookretailers/9781783989805_new.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Coupons&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please take the chance and buy your favorite Python or Django ebooks or videos form PACKT publishing. This offer is valid till &lt;strong&gt;28th of March 2016&lt;/strong&gt; so please hurry up&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For &lt;a href="https://www.packtpub.com/tech/python#/?utm_source=RP-Emadmokhtar&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=OMEPython"&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; books and videos use &lt;strong&gt;PYTHON50&lt;/strong&gt; code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For &lt;a href="https://www.packtpub.com/tech/django#/?utm_source=RP-Emadmokhtar&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=OMEDjango"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt; books and videos use  &lt;strong&gt;DJANGO50&lt;/strong&gt; code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2016 12:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2016-02-17:/packt-publishing-ebooks-and-videos-50-discount-offer.html</guid><category>django</category><category>python</category><category>ebooks</category></item><item><title>Send Emails Asynchronously from Django</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/send-emails-asynchronously-from-django.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In this article you will learn:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to send emails from &lt;a href="https://www.djangoproject.com"&gt;Django&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to use &lt;a href="http://www.celeryproject.org/"&gt;Celery&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/pmclanahan/django-celery-email"&gt;Django-Celery-Email&lt;/a&gt; to send email asynchronously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week I had the chance to get my hand dirty with Celery, I used it to send emails from Django project asynchronously using Django app call djnago-celery-email. What am I mean by sending emails asynchronously? I mean that user doesn’t wait for SMTP/mail server to send email message and give feedback to the web server, instead Django will call the send email procedure, pass it to Celery to do it away from Django application, so that user won’t wait, for example you want to send email to customer once he save customer information, you don’t want to keep user wait for application to save the customer data and send email, by sending email asynchronously user will only wait for saving confirmation and sending email celery will take care of it in the background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Alt Text" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/1442310863_full.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let’s see how we can do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Step 1: Install and Setup Celery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In terminal, active your &lt;a href="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/2015/03/virtual-environment/"&gt;virtualenv&lt;/a&gt; and type &lt;code&gt;$ pip install django-celery&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Now celery and its Django app djcelery are installed into your virtualenv.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next step is …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2016 12:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2016-01-24:/send-emails-asynchronously-from-django.html</guid><category>django</category><category>python</category><category>celery</category><category>emails</category></item><item><title>My Experience with Fitbit Customer Service</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/my-experience-with-fitbit-customer-service.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="fitbit-logo" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/fitbit-logo.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The start&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I received Fitbit Flex as my birthday gift from my wife and I joined Fitbit community since 2013, I love the device and I love the sleep tracking feature, and with this feature now I can know why I'm feeling sleepy by data. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less than one year of using my Fitbit Flex, it started to not charging, and vibrating for alarms and feedback, so I created a support issue on Fibit support portal, and the quick answer was, Oh we are sorry please give us an address so we can send you another one. I got shocked, this reminded me of Amazon Customer Service quality. &lt;img alt="fitbit support 01" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/Screenshot-2016-01-05-14.15.50.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Second Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After receiving the second Fitbit Flex, I used it for while and the wristband got damaged, I created a support issue again, they request a confirmation that my band is damaged, I replied with images, and boom the same response "Oh we are sorry please give us an address so we can send you another one". &lt;img alt="Fitbit Support 02" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/Screenshot-2016-01-05-14.22.55.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Third Issue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My replacement Fitbit Flex got damaged also and again I created support issue, and this time they were more awesome than before, they sent me a replacement though my warranty is …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 06 Jan 2016 12:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2016-01-06:/my-experience-with-fitbit-customer-service.html</guid><category>review</category></item><item><title>DotPen review</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/dotpen-review.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I bought an iPad Mini 2 to write paper-less/eletronic notes instead of having notebook and a pen always inside my pockets, I &lt;a href="/2015/12/paperless-notes/"&gt;blogged about it before&lt;/a&gt;, but I upgraded my stylus from &lt;a href="http://www.moshi.com/peripheral-stylus-pen-stanza-duo"&gt;Moshi Stanza Duo&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="http://dot-tec.com/"&gt;DotPen&lt;/a&gt;, and I want to share my experince with you. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;My Experience&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TL;DR&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want a stylus that is perfect for hand writing, buy &lt;a href="http://amzn.to/1OmUCfX"&gt;DotPen&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="dotpen" src="http://dot-tec.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/09/dot-pen-blown.png"&gt; I'm using DotPen now for two month, and I'm so happy about it, it feel like writing on paper but instead I'm writing on my iPad mini 2, and best part that it can support any note taking app, I'm using it with GoodNotes and Penultimate and it's perfectly working with them. Here is comparison between my handwriting on paper and on iPad using dotPen. &lt;img alt="paper-less Note" src="/wp-content/uploads/IMG_4280.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Some Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's not bluetooth stylus which can sync with apps to enable plam rejection feature, so that why I recommned using it with Goodnotes becasue of the writing panel. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has On/Off button which I found it's taking it really off, my iPad mini 2 can't recognize its tip if it's off.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It take AAA battery which can run it for 2 weeks at least, you won't change the …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2015 12:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2015-12-28:/dotpen-review.html</guid><category>review</category></item><item><title>Extend Django User Model and Generic Class Based View "GCBV"</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/extend-django-user-model-and-generic-class-based-view-gcbv.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1450356512_full.png" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/1450356512_full.png"&gt; When I started to learn Django, I used to use the function based view aka FBV and in my current project I decided to learn class based view CBV, I watched one &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BJiOERA49ZQ"&gt;DjangoCon videos by Andrew Pinkham&lt;/a&gt; to make this easier on me, and if you tried or planning to learn CBV, you will be confused about the class based views and the generic class based views inside Django, it’s some many of them, please watch the video to get your head around it. OK, now I’ve done my homework and it’s time to use CBV, believe me it’s easy and you will find the number of code lines inside our views will be decreased specially if you use GCBV. User Model and GCBV &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;What is the relation between GCBV and User Model?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great question, while I’m working with one of my models fro example her the Teacher model, and teacher will has a user credentials in order to user the app. The easiest and the straightforward way is to make one-to-one relation with &lt;a href="https://github.com/django/django/blob/53ccffdb8c8e47a4d4304df453d8c79a9be295ab/django/contrib/auth/models.py"&gt;django.contrib.auth.models.User&lt;/a&gt; please read the quote from Django documentation: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two ways to extend the default User …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2015 12:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2015-12-18:/extend-django-user-model-and-generic-class-based-view-gcbv.html</guid><category>Django</category><category>Python</category></item><item><title>My journey from paper note to paperless note</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/my-journey-from-paper-note-to-paperless-note.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/wp-content/uploads/1450004669_full.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="paperless note on iPad" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/1450004669_full.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really love to take notes wherever and wheneve. I like to keep my notes with me, but after buying iPad mini I decide to change my note tool from paper notes to paperless notes (e-notes), but I like to hand writing my notes I want something that feels like paper notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Searching for the tool&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought of buying a stylus for iPad that feels like real pen and start taking notes, first I found &lt;a href="https://www.fiftythree.com/pencil"&gt;fiftythree Pencil&lt;/a&gt; but it was built mainly for designers not for writing, then I found The best stylus for me is the &lt;a href="http://www.adonit.net/jot/script/"&gt;Jot Script&lt;/a&gt; but it is expensive but it has the best writing experience and best accuracy. This is for the stylus, for the application I searched about note application that can enhance my writing accuracy, I found two note apps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://evernote.com/penultimate/"&gt;Penultimate Evernote&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Free&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sync with Evernote&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zoom in and write with line recognition&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.goodnotesapp.com/"&gt;Goodnotes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paid  (but worth every penny)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Backup with most of cloud storages like Google Driver, Dropbox, &amp;amp; OneDrive.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pen size &amp;amp; color customization.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Palm rest and palm rejection.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add annotations to PDF files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing panel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shape recognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;My final tools&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Device:&lt;/strong&gt; iPad mini with retina display.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Note App:&lt;/strong&gt; Goodnotes.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Stylus:&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;a href="http://www.moshi.com/peripheral-stylus-pen-stanza-duo"&gt;Moshi …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 13 Dec 2015 11:47:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2015-12-13:/my-journey-from-paper-note-to-paperless-note.html</guid><category>notes</category><category>papreless</category></item><item><title>Solution for psycopg2 installation error with Mac OSX El Capitan</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/solution-for-psycopg2-installation-error-with-mac-osx-el-capitan.html</link><description>&lt;h1&gt;The Issue&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you tried to install to install psycopg2 package after upgrading to Mac OSX El Capitan and got an error like this:     &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;xcrun&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;error&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;invalid&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;active&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;developer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;path&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Library&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sr"&gt;/Developer/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;CommandLineTools&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class="n"&gt;missing&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;xcrun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;at&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="sr"&gt;/Library/Developer/CommandLineTools/usr/bin/x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;crun&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="pip.log" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/1444569163_full.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Soltuion:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simplly install Command-Line Tools:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo xcode-select --install&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 11 Oct 2015 12:00:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2015-10-11:/solution-for-psycopg2-installation-error-with-mac-osx-el-capitan.html</guid><category>developement</category><category>macosx</category></item><item><title>CodeWars.com Can Improve Your Problem Solving Skill</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/codewarscom-can-improve-your-problem-solving-skill.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Codewars logo" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/1444038896_full.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I posted that &lt;a href="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/2015/05/warning-your-daily-job-can-kill-your-skills/"&gt;your daily job can kill your skills&lt;/a&gt;, and I mentioned specifically the problem solving skill, as a software developer problem solving skill is one of the most important and key skill you need to master to be a good developer, in the post I mentioned that I started to solve code puzzles on &lt;a href="http://codeeval.com/"&gt;CodeEval.com&lt;/a&gt;, it is good but during one of &lt;a href="https://www.livecoding.tv"&gt;livecoding.tv&lt;/a&gt; session the developer mentioned &lt;a href="http://codewars.com/"&gt;CodeWars.com&lt;/a&gt; and I thought to give it a try, so I signed in and start to solve some puzzles aka katas and get higher in rank, and I discovered the differences and why &lt;a href="http://codewars.com/"&gt;CodeWars.com&lt;/a&gt; is better from my perspective.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;CodeWars advantages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In CodeWars you’ll start to solve puzzles (it’s called kata) from starting rank (easy katas) toward much harder ones and this is common in code puzzles website, but what is special about CodeWars:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Check others solutions: &lt;/strong&gt;After post your solution you can view others solutions, and this can really help you in crafting the skill, for example you solved one kata and after you checked others solutions, you discovered better solutions “WOW these guys solved it in very clean way", and now you …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 09:57:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2015-10-05:/codewarscom-can-improve-your-problem-solving-skill.html</guid><category>codeing</category><category>skills</category><category>problem solving</category></item><item><title>Solo Developer</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/solo-developer.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Developers and coders are known as anti-social but after many years in development field, I can tell you this is totally wrong and developers who can communicate well are good developers they can learn and understand what they are really doing, if you read soft skills books for developers, sure you will find chapter about communications and How to be a part of software development team, but if you can’t communicate with your teammate you’ll always work lonely and gain nothing more than loneliness and coding in the dark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I joined the software industry 4+ years, and I’m working, coding, and developing alone, I read about pair programming in XP “eXtreme Programming” and daily standup meetings in SCRUM, and How it can increase the quality and productivity of teams, but I didn’t experience those, I never pair programming and never being in one of Agile methodologies, but I’m trying to think with someone else not in the same team and not a developer, but it worth trying because it’s really amazing, you’ll feel like you have two extra minds, yes as you read it, it is like 1 + 1 = 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you …&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2015 09:45:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2015-07-08:/solo-developer.html</guid><category>developer</category><category>programming</category></item><item><title>Initial Review: Becoming Steve Jobs</title><link>http://www.emadmokhtar.com/initial-review-becoming-steve-jobs.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Becomming Steve Jobs book cover" src="http://www.emadmokhtar.com/images/1431938096_full.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until now I finished 35% of &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0385347405/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0385347405&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=monsblo08-20&amp;amp;linkId=2SJY4Q5N7KFZ52DB"&gt;Becoming Steve Jobs: The Evolution of a Reckless Upstart into a Visionary Leader&lt;/a&gt; book, and I don’t find Steve Jobs a successful entrepreneur or even a leader. Apple's first success because of Apple I which is Steve Wozniak idea and engineered by him as well, and Pixar was succeed because of its leader not Steve Jobs, in fact Steve Jobs was the reason for projects like (Apple III, Macintosh, and NeXT workstations) to fail, and was trying to make Pixar the next failure but its leaders keep him away and done what they knew it's right for Pixar. In the nutshell Steve Jobs is bad micromanager that you shouldn't dream to be like him, for me he is a fake leader.&lt;br&gt;
I’ll continue the book to see How did he turn to be the visionary leader after that :)&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Emad Mokhtar</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2015 08:35:00 +0300</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:www.emadmokhtar.com,2015-05-18:/initial-review-becoming-steve-jobs.html</guid><category>book</category><category>review</category></item></channel></rss>